Maitraye Das

maitrave.github.io maitraye@u.northwestern.edu

Research Statement

My research interest falls broadly in the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Accessibility. Specifically, my doctoral research involves studying and designing for accessible collaborative content production in ability-diverse teams. My work draws on literature in HCI, CSCW, and critical disability studies to uncover how accessibility is created, negotiated, and sustained in collaborative work. Methodologically, I take a cross-disciplinary approach that includes qualitative methods (e.g., contextual interviews, observations, ethnography) as well as system design, development, and evaluation through controlled experiments and design exploration studies. As a HCI researcher, my broader goal is to support accessibility through design and thus, contribute towards reducing equity gaps in education, employment, and creative expression.

Education

NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

EVANSTON, IL, USA

PhD in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication)

Fall 2017 - Present

Dissertation: Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments Committee: Darren Gergle (co-chair), Anne Marie Piper (co-chair), Marcelo Worsley, and Cynthia Bennett

NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

EVANSTON, IL, USA

MS in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication)

Mar 2021

Sep 2015

GPA: 3.97 out of 4.00

BANGLADESH UNIVERSITY OF ENGINEERING & TECHNOLOGY (BUET)

BANGLADESH

BS in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

GPA: 3.85 out of 4.00 (top 6% of the graduating class)

Research Experience

COLLABORATIVE TECHNOLOGY LAB | NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

Fall 2017 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant | advised by Darren Gergle

Conducted contextual interviews and observations to understand collaborative writing practices and accessibility needs of visually impaired writers. Developed audio enhancements for asynchronous collaborative writing and evaluated through a mixed-methods controlled experimental study. Currently developing non-visual interactions to support accessibility in synchronous collaborative writing for visually impaired writers. [CSCW 2019]

INCLUSIVE TECHNOLOGY LAB | NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

Spring 2018 – Present

Graduate Researcher | advised by Anne Marie Piper

Conducted ethnographic field observations and contextual interviews at a weaving studio for people with vision impairments. Designed auditory augmentations on a loom to enhance collaborative weaving experiences among blind weavers and their sighted instructors. Currently developing an audio-tactile system to support collaborative designing of fabric patterns for blind weavers. [CHI 2020, TACCESS]

ABILITY TEAM | MICROSOFT RESEARCH, USA

Summer 2020

Research Intern | mentored by John Tang

Conducted semi-structured interviews with 36 neurodivergent professionals. Performed thematic analysis to highlight accessibility issues in remote work during the COVID-19 pandemic. [CSCW 2021]

PEOPLE, SPACE & ALGORITHMS GROUP | NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY Fall 2017 – Summer 2018 Graduate Researcher | mentored by Brent Hecht

Collected a dataset of nearly 0.45 billion edits by 2000 OpenStreetMap editors using Python and Osmium. Performed quantitative analysis to investigate gender-based self-focus bias in OpenStreetMap. [CHI 2019]

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, USA

Summer 2017

Researcher (remote) | mentored by Moushumi Sharmin and Shameem Ahmed

Performed a systematic literature review on the design of smart technologies for children on the autism spectrum. [CHI 2018]

> Maitraye Das | p. 1 Last updated 3/22/21

BANGLADESH UNIVERSITY OF ENGINEERING & TECHNOLOGY

Undergraduate Researcher | advised by Tanzima Hashem

 Developed a secret sharing algorithm for privacy-preserved and authenticated queries in genomic databases to compute disease susceptibility. [COMPSAC 2018, Journal of Information Processing 2019]

Honors, Awards, & Grants

Graduate Research Grant Northwestern University (\$2,999)	2021-22
Finalist Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award ACM CHI [C1]	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award ACM CSCW [J4]	2019
Special Recognition for Outstanding Review ACM CHI'21 (3 times), ACM CSCW'19	2021, 2019
Conference Travel Grant Northwestern University (\$2,300 + \$1,500)	2019, 2018
Best Paper Award IEEE COMPSAC [C4]	2018
Student Travel Grant ACM UbiComp (\$600)	2018
Student Scholarship Grace Hopper Celebration, USA	2018
Best Undergraduate Thesis Award Dept. of CSE, Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2015
Best Technical Poster Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Student Scholarship Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Dean's List Award Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2011-2015
University Merit Scholarship Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2011-2014

Journal Articles

- J1. **Maitraye Das,** Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. Design and Evaluation of Collaborative Writing Techniques for People with Vision Impairments. Under review in *ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*. Impact Factor: 3.147.
- J2. **Maitraye Das,** John Tang, Kathryn E. Ringland, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Towards Accessible Remote Work: Understanding Work-from-Home Practices of Neurodivergent Professionals. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 5, CSCW1, Article 183 (April 2021), 30 pages.
- J3. Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, Maitraye Das, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Melodie: A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting through Audio-Enhanced Weaving. In ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS). Impact Factor: 2.641.
- Q J4. Maitraye Das, Darren Gergle, and Anne Marie Piper. 2019. "It doesn't win you friends": Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 3, CSCW, Article 191 (November 2019), 26 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3359293 [acceptance rate: 31.2%] *Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
 - J5. Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Maitraye Das, Tanzima Hashem, Sharmin Afrose, and Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar. 2019. Towards Privacy-preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries. In *Journal of Information Processing*, Vol. 27, (September 2019), pp. 624-642. DOI: 10.2197/ipsjiip.27.624

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers¹

- Q C1. Maitraye Das, Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Weaving by Touch: A Case Analysis of Accessible Making. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20), 1-15. DOI: 10.1145/3313831.3376477 [acceptance rate: 24.3%]
 - *Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
 - C2. **Maitraye Das,** Brent Hecht, and Darren Gergle. 2019. The Gendered Geography of Contributions to OpenStreetMap: Complexities in Self-Focus Bias. In *Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19)*, Paper 563, 14 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3290605.3300793 [acceptance rate: 23.8%]

¹ Peer-reviewed conferences such as CHI are <u>top-tier publication venues in Human-Computer Interaction</u>. They are highly selective, extensively reviewed, and intended for archival papers only. When available, the acceptance rate is included.

- C3. Moushumi Sharmin, Monsur Hossain, Abir Saha, Maitraye Das, Margot Maxwell, and Shameem Ahmed. 2018. From Research to Practice: Informing the Design of Autism Support Smart Technology. In Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '18), Paper 102, 1-16. DOI: 10.1145/3173574.3173676 [acceptance rate: 25%]
- P C4. Maitraye Das, Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Sharmin Afrose, Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar, and Tanzima Hashem.
 2018. A Novel Secret Sharing Approach for Privacy-Preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries in
 Genomic Databases. In Proceedings of the 42nd IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications
 (COMPSAC '18), pp. 645-654. DOI: 10.1109/COMPSAC.2018.00097 [acceptance rate: 24%]

 *Best Paper Award

 *Best Paper Award

 *Best Paper Award

 **Best Paper Award
 - C5. Abir Saha and **Maitraye Das**. 2017. Impact of Social Networking on Post-Partum Depression in Women: An Analysis in the context of Bangladesh. In *Proceedings of the 20th IEEE International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '17)*, pp. 1-6. DOI: 10.1109/ICCITECHN.2017.8281831
 - C6. **Maitraye Das** and Abir Saha. 2017. An Automated Speech-Language Therapy Tool with Interactive Virtual Agent and Peer-to-Peer Feedback. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE '17)*, pp. 510-515, DOI: 10.1109/ICAEE.2017.8255409
 - C7. Fatema Khan, **Maitraye Das**, and Ahiya Ahammed. 2016. PurpleAid: An mHealth platform to combat health hazards of women. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Medical Engineering, Health Informatics and Technology (MediTec '16*), pp. 1-6. DOI: 10.1109/MEDITEC.2016.7835368
 - C8. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Syeda Lammim Ahad. 2016. A Novel Health Support System with Biometric Data Acquisition Device. In *Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '16)*, pp. 201-206. DOI: 10.1109/ICCITECHN.2016.7860195

Refereed Workshop Short Papers, Posters, and Doctoral Consortia

- 1. **Maitraye Das.** 2020. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In 2020 Conference Companion Publication on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '20). DOI: 10.1145/3406865.3418369 [Doctoral Consortium]
- 2. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Rethinking Power and Politics in Accessible Making. In *ACM CHI Workshop* "Nothing About Us Without Us": Investigating the Role of Critical Disability Studies in HCI.
- Maitraye Das. 2019. Who Can See What: Privacy and Audience Management for People with Vision Impairments on Social Media. In ACM CSCW Workshop on Addressing the Accessibility of Social Media.
- Maitraye Das. 2018. Understanding Collaborative Writing Practices of People with Visual Impairments. In Proceedings of the 2018 ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp '18), pp. 1744-1749. DOI: 10.1145/3267305.3277807
- 5. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Towards Understanding the Effects of Social Networking on Postpartum Depression in Women. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- 6. **Maitraye Das**, Sharmin Afrose, and Tanzima Hashem. 2015. Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- 7. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Shahina Ferdous. 2014. SpeechAid: A Self-treatment System for Individuals with Speech Disorder. In *Grace Hopper Celebration India*. *Best Technical Poster Award

Teaching Experience

UNITED INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY (UIU)

DHAKA, BANGLADESH Oct 2015 – Mar 2017

Lecturer | Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

 Instructed courses on Computer Architecture, Digital Logic Design, Electrical Circuits and Assembly Programming Language.

Skills

Programming: Python, R, C, C++, Java, HTML, CSS

Research Methods: Interviews, contextual observations, ethnography, thematic analysis, grounded theory method, survey design, experiment design, quantitative analysis, prototyping

Students Mentored

Thomas McHugh Undergrad in Computer Science, Northwestern University	2020-Present
Rawan Mohamed Undergrad in Computer Science, Northwestern University	2020
Caroline Brewley High school student researcher	2019
Nusrat Jahan Mozumder Undergrad in CSE, Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology	2017-2018
Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar Undergrad in CSE, Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology	y 2017-2018
Fatema Khan Undergrad in CSE, United International University	2016
Ahiya Ahammed Undergrad in CSE, United International University	2016

Invited Talks

Input and Interaction (INFO 463) | University of Washington

Nov 2020

Guest lecture: Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments (virtual)

Bangladesh HCI and ICTD Study and Research Group, Virtual Event

April 2020

Talk: Designing for Accessible Interaction

Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship Finalist Presentation | Redmond, WA, USA

Nov 2019

Poster: Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments

Academic Services

Program Committee Member

Shadow PC, ACM COMPASS	2021
Reviewer	
ACM CHI [*outstanding review recognitions: 3]	2021
ACM CSCW [*outstanding review recognition: 1]	2019 2020

ACM CSCW [*outstanding review recognition: 1]	2019-2020
ACM DIS	2020
GHC Faculty Scholarship	2017
Australasian Database Conference	2016

Student Volunteer	
ACM CHI	2021, 2019
ACM CSCW	2019
ACM UbiComp	2018
InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2018

Publicity Co-chair	
InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2019

Outreach & Memberships

Co-host & Co-organizer	2020 - Present
------------------------	----------------

Inspiring Stories (podcast series on Bangladeshi women in STEM)

Member

Northwestern Graduate Women in Computing	2019 - Present
Association for Computing Machinery (ACM), SIGCHI, SIGACCESS	2017 - Present
Bangladeshi Women in Computer Science and Engineering	2015 - Present

Code Coach Volunteer

BraveCamp Chicago (non-profit coding camp for high school girls)

Summer 2018

Vice-President

Murchhona: BUET (cultural club) 2014 – 2015